ten artists remain however only one of
you will earn $100,000 a feature in
Inked Magazine and the title of ink
master to stay in this competition you
must fight side by side with your team
for every advantage but a team is only
as strong as its leader this week both
of your coaches are innovative and
eccentric artists that tackle things
with their own style James Vaughn and
Megan Jean Morris welcome back hey good
to see you coaches your team survival is
on your shoulders save all your artists
from elimination and you'll earn a spot
in the clash of the coaches face-off for
$25,000 when I was here I felt like
there was just no one I could trust even
your own friends want to see you lose so
I want to be the person in the corner
for my team I'm someone you could bounce
an idea off of and I'll give you my real
opinion to defeat the enemy you must
know the enemy so James you'll coach the
women's team and Megan Jean you'll coach
the men's team go ahead join your teams
I don't feel like coaching the female
team that I'm not strange at all I have
three daughters and all I do is live
with women so I could kind of get them
to understand my point of view and not
offend anybody this week we are testing
composition that's something we don't
like composition is taking multiple
elements and putting them in one design
so that they have flow and balance for
this flash challenge you must create an
impressive three-dimensional design
one toothpick at a time lord have mercy
I thought I've seen it all but this is
the craziest shit ever in this room are
nearly half a million toothpicks you
must work as a team to glue each
toothpick together weaving a flowing
design of shapes and textures to bring a
mind-blowing well composed sculpture to
life this isn't a challenge I would pick
we are looking for a three-dimensional
sculpture we are looking for creativity
but most of all we want to see
composition since it is a 3d image it
should have a great flowing composition
that like a sculpture you can look at it
from any direction and it looks cool
work it girls win this challenge and
your team will have the power to assign
all the human canvases in the
Elimination tattoo let's get it again we
definitely need that we really do yeah
you'll have seven hours and your time
starts now
somebody grab a drawing pad guys come
here I need to say a couple things on my
season I want every single flash
challenge until they didn't listen to me
I'm gonna tell you what I know testing
composition they're gonna have to create
a couple different elements that play
together well so that they can compose
an image what if we did like a teepee in
my mind that'll be very elementary if
you do something flat then the idea of
composition isn't there
my thought was possibly like a cherry
blossom tree that was my first thought
to was to do a little tree okay
this challenge could be very tedious
this is the kind of thing that people
spend weeks months and years on these
guys only have a few hours my initial
idea is doing a castle it's almost the
first idea that someone would have so to
me it's not actually that creative I'm
an artist I don't want to see something
I've seen a hundred thousand times
before my ideas are more abstract a
shape like this just flat tears a big
ball at the top right at the pinnacle of
the thing the ball is like slightly
leaning like it wants to go and then you
just have like one little guy like
pushing the ball like uphill trying to
get it over I just don't know how we're
gonna make little what is a toothpick I
do I've thought about it like there
stick figures it's just expression it
ladies and gentlemen six hours to go why
are we making this tree at the base wide
enough to be heavy enough to hold the
rest of the branches over to show
composition with a tree is great because
it's got branches we can branch out into
all different dimensions and make sure
we even get flow and look really
cohesive how will stand so if it have
roots that were like holding itself on
the table they will help manage the
weight on this side okay I think
hopefully we can get another guy out of
here to keep the women count above the
men count okay this is a lot more
flexible
yes thank you my dear that's what you
know yes you're so smart we have to make
sure that there are three girls in this
finale so the more girls that we keep
the more likely it is that that's gonna
happen
do you think that Oliver gets splinters
and his mom he's got to I mean you're
using toothpicks maybe that's why he's
so cranky
he got splinters in his mouth
yeah this is Derek you're gonna take a
ton of these to cover the whole law what
are they doing I don't know how we're
gonna show composition because I don't
even know what this is
how strong are these guys just one of
them try yeah that's business chart of
mine what I can understand we're doing a
giant ball which is representing a rock
as we pushed up by a bunch of little
dudes that's gonna smush some guy on the
ground and I think that's supposed to be
me when you guys think about having a
dung beetle pushing up a pile of shit
off the bridge have you kind of cool you
know what else would be kind of cool not
losing again
three hours left three hours left guys
[Music]
I'm not gonna lie I feel like
personality-wise I click the best with
Jason and cam and I feel like I'm
getting a little bit too far in with
that friendship in the end don't fight
for them when it comes down to our team
as women I feel like I'm going down a
road that I don't want to go down I'm
such a frazzled person I don't even know
what I'm doing half the time let alone
trying to strategize the strategy is not
a bad thing but when you're strategizing
against your own team is when it gets
shady and you want me to be cool I did
not freak out right because they're
trying to get us straight into the
finale David of the day my team is the
only thing that has ever come first but
not everybody can have loyalty or
dignity or integrity anything besides
being us come back somebody's gonna get
a toothpick to the neck today
what are they doing blowing their stuff
on the side like that this is like a
titanic situation we're gonna put it
together in the end that's good
same kind of spin boys this is your
final hour everybody it's just resting
do we care how are we gonna do the
little people on the bridge we get one
people on that bridge at this point
there's a decent chance this will have
it stick out look this way it's a little
dude time oh my god stop it right now
he's so cute I love this hat three two
one that's it
time is up I should be good everybody
back away carefully Fonda awesome
look already dude catching the ball it
works we can't even get close to ours
you can actually touch yours don't go by
it
don't go by it seriously all right guys
it is now time to critique your work
let's start with a men's team the
struggle is real in here and the
struggles real on there the fact that
there's motion and teamwork and it's
kind of telling your story that's a nice
thing the little figures are killer
where you guys really do well is your
spiral and the concept of what it is the
pathways cool I like the idea of the
figures therefore the teamwork as far as
thinking outside the box and showing
something artistic I think you guys do
that at least I don't feel like it's
lame I'm happy with it
alright women's team you're up next
Steve make a really beautiful piece
she's got great dynamics it does have a
great composition the limbs have a nice
flow I really like the root system
coming down looking flat against the
surface and curving around the corners
and all the little tricks you used to
make this thing really come together I
can say y'all really made a beautiful
piece of art well ours too
composition well we intentionally went
like you're minimalist with it
[Music]